Finding Aid for the Hollywood Studio Strike Collection LSC.0226
UCLA Library Special Collections
Hollywood Studio Strike collection
1944-1985
1944-1948
UCLA Library Special Collections
LSC.0226
2.0 linear feet (4 boxes)
1.5 linear feet (1 unprocessed flat box)
The Hollywood studio strike began on March 12, 1945 when the Conference of Studio Unions (CSU) went on strike to protest the studios' delay in granting a contract renewal for interior decorators despite opposition from the larger, more established International Alliance of Theatrical Stage Employees and Moving Picture Operators of the United States and Canada (IATSE). The collection consists of materials dealing with the studio strike of 1945 and the International Alliance of Theatrical Stage Employees and Moving Picture Machine Operators of the United States and Canada (IATSE).
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of Screen Publicists Guild, 1945.
Gift of Gene Mailes, 1960-85.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9917204893606533
Biography
The Hollywood studio strike began on March 12, 1945 when the Conference of Studio Unions (CSU) went on strike to protest the studios' delay in granting a contract renewal for interior decorators despite opposition from the larger, more established International Alliance of Theatrical Stage Employees and Moving Picture Operators of the United States and Canada (IATSE). The collection consists of materials dealing with the studio strike of 1945 and the International Alliance of Theatrical Stage Employees and Moving Picture Machine Operators of the United States and Canada (IATSE).
Biographica Note from original paper finding aid:
The Hollywood studio strike began on March 12, 1945 when the Conference of Studio Unions (CSU), consisting of nine unions and nearly ten thousand workers led by Herbert Sorrell, went on strike to protest the studios' delay in granting a contract renewal for interior decorators despite opposition from the larger, more established International Alliance of Theatrical Stage Employees and Moving Picture Operators of the United States and Canada (IATSE). In early October 1945, CSU concentrated its pickets at Warner Brothers; a series of fights ensued and police, studio guards, and IATSE forced the strikers to retreat. At the end of October, the National Labor Relations Board ruled in favor of CSU, and the studios and IATSE gave way. In early 1946, CSU tried to negotiate a new wage contract with the studios, but disagreements lead to another strike in the summer of 1946. IASTE sent their employees to keep the studios open, provoking more armed clashes. The Screen Actors Guild and 24 other Hollywood unions denounced the strike as a jurisdictional dispute, affirming their right to cross the picket lines. CSU's failure to close the studios led to a vote in October 1947 by the painters union which broke the strike; CSU disintegrated and faded away.
Scope and Content
Collection consists of materials dealing with the Hollywood studio strike of 1945 and the International Alliance of Theatrical Stage Employees and Moving Picture Machine Operators of the United States and Canada (IATSE). Includes newspaper clippings from the Hollywood Sun and the Conference of Studio Unions (CSU) news, mimeographed statements to union members, correspondence, ephemera, and a copy of the IATSE proceedings with taped reminiscences of Gene Mailes.
Organization and Arrangement
Arranged in the following series:
Correspondence and ephemera.
National Labor Relations Board materials and union newspapers.
Copy of IATSE proceedings, audio tape of Gene Mailes' reminiscences of proceedings, and printed materials (1945-85).
Related Material
You Don't Choose Your Friends: the Memoirs of Herbert Knott Sorrell [oral history transcript] / Herbert Knott Sorrell, interviewee. UCLA Oral History Department interview, 1963. Available at UCLA Library Special Collections.
Audiotapes.; Strikes and lockouts -- Motion picture industry -- California -- Los Angeles -- Archives.; Motion picture industry -- Employees -- Labor unions -- United States -- Archives.; International Alliance of Theatrical Stage Employees and Moving Picture Machine Operators of the United States and Canada.; Mailes, Gene; United States--National Labor Relations Board.
- Correspondence and Ephemera Material
  - Conference of Studio Unions. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents note
    Various printed material dealing with the C.S.U. also folder 1A (added August 1969).
  - Correspondence--Abroad. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - IATSE (International Alliance of Theatrical Stage Employees). (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Information Bulletin. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - IATSE. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence (Brewer, Walsh). (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - IATSE, Local 683. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - IATSE, Local 683. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Film Technician's Daily Bulletin, November 1946-June 1947. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - IATSE, Local 705. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Inter-faith Council of Los Angeles. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Leaflets. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - McKnight, Russell L. (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Manuscript material. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Miscellaneous. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Miscellaneous ephemera. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Press Lists. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Press releases. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Strike trials. (Box 1, Folder 16)
- National Labor Relations Board Materials and Union Newspapers
  - U.S. Department of Labor, Wage and Hour division. (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - N.L.R.B.--Decorator's Case. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - IATSE Disciplinary hearings, testimony typescript, pp.2424-2565. (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - IATSE Disciplinary hearings appeal and N.L.R.B. decision. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Costumer's News. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - CSU News vol.1 no.4-36, incomplete., November 1946-August 1947. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Hollywood Atom vol.1 no.1-43, incomplete., August-November 1945. (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Hollywood Close-up, 8 numbers, incomplete., November 1945-July 1946. (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Union Newspapers and Miscellaneous Clippings
  - Hollywood Sun, vol.1 no.2-16. Incomplete, May-August 1945. (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Hollywood Sun, vol.1 no.18-32. Incomplete, September-December 1945. (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Hollywood Sun, vol.2 no.1-26. Incomplete, January-June 1946. (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Hollywood Sun, vol.3 no.1-21. Incomplete, July-November 1946. (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Hollywood Sun, vol.4 no.7-10., February-March 1947. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Los Angeles Times. Incomplete, May 1947-March 1948. (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - The Progressive Citizen. (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - The Union Labor Sun, vol.4 no.12-24., March 26-June 11, 1947. (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Daily Variety. (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Scattered issues and clippings. (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous newspapers. (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous clippings. (Box 3, Folder 11)
    General note
    Additional materials donated March 1985.
- Cassette tape recordings of Gene Mailes' reminiscences relating to the IATSE proceedings and related copy proceedings and printed materials, ca. 1945-1985. (Box 4)